Daf is Lamed. We pick up on the bottom of Kaf Tet
Amud Bet. And we're dealing with the idea of a Shliach appointing
another Shliach, and when it's in Eretz Yisrael—when it's from Chutz La'aretz—he
needs to do it in front of Beis Din to say Befanai
Nechtav. And we turn
to—and the Gemara introduced an idea of Shliach shelo nitan l'geirushin, who
a Shliach is not made to actually do the divorce himself, and
that person is not fully empowered and therefore cannot hand over, transfer
the responsibility of giving the Get. So the Gemara sort of said
that that wasn't the case there, but it introduced the idea. So
now we pick up with Hahu Gavra. It is ten lines from
the bottom, beginning of the word, beginning of the line.
Hahu Gavra dishadar leh gitta l'vei itteih—a man sent a Get to
his wife. Amar leh l'shliach and said to the Shliach: Lo titein
lah ad t'latasin yomin—don't give it to her until thirty days. Okay?
Ifnas b'go t'latasin yomin—so this guy within thirty days, he was there,
he was planning on being in Miami for like, you know, six
weeks, but then something happened and he had to leave. So he
couldn't wait until the end of thirty days to give it to
her. All right? So he had to leave. It wasn't valid to
be given, like was postdated—not literally postdated, but whatever—it wasn't valid to
be given for thirty days. So now what's he going to do?
So asa l'kamei d'Rava—he came to Rava. Amar Rava—so Rava said: Chala
ta'ama mai—why does the Mishna teach that a Shliach can appoint another
Shliach in a case when he gets sick, right? The Gemara described
before that it might have to be Davka because he got sick.
Okay? So—so that's when you're allowed to appoint another Shliach. So Chala
ta'ama
mai? Mishum de'anus—because it's out of his hands, can't control it, and
we would assume that the husband would not mind for it to
be handed over in that type of a case, that responsibility of
giving the Get. So hai nami anus hu—so this case also is
an anus and therefore it can be handed over. Okay, fine. It's
a good case like the Mishna where he can't do it himself
and he's able to give over that responsibility. So amar leh—so he
said to him: Mesoru
milach kamei didan—give over your words in front of us, presumably there
was a Beis Din there. So say Befanai Nechtav in our presence.
D'levatar t'latasin yomin mashvinan shliach v'yahiv lah as that after
and then we will take on that responsibility and we'll
make a Shliach after thirty days to give her the Get. Very
good, very nice. All like the Mishna. Giving it over, saying it
in front of a Beis Din, the Beis Din will appoint a
Shliach. It's a case of Chala, perfect application of the Mishna. Amar
leh Rabanan l'Rava—so the Rabbis said to Rava: Ve'ha shliach shelo nitan
l'geirushin
hu—same challenge as before. How can he give over that responsibility to
a Beis Din? He is not yet empowered to give it himself.
His Shlichus is sort of on hold until the end of thirty
days, right? He hasn't been activated yet for active duty. You know?
So he's not yet empowered to give it himself. So if he's
not empowered to give it himself, he can't give over that responsibility
to you. Amar le'hu—he said back to them: No, kevan d'levatar t'latasin
yomin matzi m'garesh—he will have that ability at the end of thirty
days, so k'shliach she'nitan l'geirushin hu—his fundamental agency is empowering him to
give the Get. Okay? He is fundamentally empowered to give the Get
at a particular time. But that does not mean—and even though that
time hasn't reached, it does not mean that we define him in
terms of his role as somebody who is not empowered. His role
is somebody who is empowered; he's just waiting for the right time
and therefore he can give over that responsibility to us. Okay? So
now the Gemara says: V'leichoosh shema piyes—one minute. If it's on hold
for thirty days, why would a
person write—why do you postdate a check? Okay? Maybe you want to
make sure that the funds are there, right? Or maybe, or maybe
you want to give yourself time to back out, to change your
mind, right? So if he's postdating it for—not the Get itself—but he's
holding putting it on hold for thirty days, maybe the husband is
giving himself time to consider whether he wants to go through with
it. Maybe he's going to make up with his wife or not.
So the Gemara says how can we go ahead and give the
Get in ignorance of what might have transpired in those last thirty
days? And maybe he made up with his wife? And then the
problem will be that it will be a Get delivered that was—between—after
it was written, before it was given, and in the interim—I'm sorry—that
in between the writing and the giving of the Get, if the
husband and wife are together in yichud and certainly if they actually
sleep together, the Get is pasul d'rabanan because people will say she'll
have gotten pregnant, we're concerned that that will have happened through that
event that occurred before the Get was given. And people will say,
right, that the—that the child was basically born out of wedlock. Right?
Is that clear what the concern is? If he says you have
to give the Get in thirty days, when is it dated?
At that thirty—no, no, no, I shouldn't be using the term postdated.
occurred before the גט get *get* was given and
people will say that the child was basically and the date was
from beforehand and people will say that the child was basically born
out of wedlock, right? Is that clear what the concern is? When
you say you have to give the גט get *get* in thirty
days, when's it dated? At that thirtieth day? No, no, no, no.
I shouldn't be using the term post-date because that's I'm trying to
use a common example but that's confusing because no, no, no, גט
get *get*, it would be the date on the גט get *get*
is the date it was written. And that's exactly what the problem
here is. It's written on January first, it's delivered on February first.
If they slept together on January fifteenth, then people will do the
math in their head and they'll look at the גט get *get*
and they'll say oh wait, it looks like this baby was born
out of wedlock because they'll think she was divorced from January first,
that's the day on the גט get *get*. That's called the problem
of a גט get ישן *get yashan*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says in this type of a case where he had the גט
get *get*, he said don't deliver it for thirty days, how can
we deliver it after thirty days if we don't know what transpired?
Maybe in the interim they slept together. And why should we be
חושש *choshesh* for that? I don't know, why did he put it
on hold for thirty days? Maybe they're trying to make up. So
how can we deliver it with that ignorance?
He's doing a second שליח shliach *shliach*, that's just a fundamental problem
with this whole thing of delivering it thirty days.
What do you mean? They're allowed to make another שליח shliach, *shliach*,
that's the משנה mishna.
*Mishna*. I understand but this problem that you just raised, even if
there wasn't a second
שליח shliach *shliach*, no, that's a good question. But here it's particularly
a problem because he said wait thirty days. If you're sending a
שליח shliach *shliach* and it takes the שליח shliach *shliach* time to
get from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz. *chutz l'aretz* to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, first of all the husband's in חוץ לארץ *chutz
l'aretz* so there's no way he's coming back to ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael* during that time and whatever, he's not around, and he's not
putting it on hold, that's just natural delays. But when he explicitly
said I want you to hold it for thirty days, well maybe
he's trying to reconcile. A, he's around, and B, the fact that
he's actively putting it on hold means he maybe wants to reconcile.
Even if he's in a different place?
Well, I don't know, that maybe, but at least but he's not
so far distant because the שליח shliach, *shliach* is waiting thirty days.
So he's putting it on hold, he's able to come and therefore
how can we go ahead and give it? But Dovber asks the
good question, it's not like a normal case of sending a גט
*get*. Here the husband can come and he is explicitly put it
on hold. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says. וניחוש
שמא פייס *ve'neichosh shema piyes*, let be concerned that he reconciled. ולא
תנן tenan, *ve'lo tnan*, did we not teach in our משנה mishna
*Mishna*, מעכשיו אם לא באתי מכאן ועד י"ב חודש *me'achshav im lo
basi mikan v'ad yud beis chodesh*, if a guy says this is
your גט *get* as of now if I don't return within twelve
months
and then he died before the twelve months, הרי זה גט *harei
zeh get*, it's a גט *get*, right, because he's not going to
come within twelve months. והוינן בה *va'havinan bah*, and we asked on
that, וניחוש שמא פייס *ve'neichosh shema piyes*,
and then we asked on that, but how can we go ahead
and say it's good? Maybe before he died he snuck back and
we don't know about it, and maybe they reconciled before he died.
ואמר רבה בר רב הונא Rav Huna. הכי אמר amar אבא מרי
משמיה דרב *ve'amar Rabba bar Rav Huna hachi amar Abba Mari mishmeih
deRav*, here's what Abba Mari says in the name of Rav, באומר
נאמנת עלי לומר שלא באתי *be'omer ne'emenes alai lomar shelo basi*, that
if the case where he says that if there's no evidence that
I didn't come, my wife or even if I maybe claim that
I came, well it won't be relevant that he's dead, but anyway
my wife is believed to me more than a hundred eighty, more
than my own claim, she's believed to testify whether I did or
did not come.
So that's why it works and we don't have to be afraid
he came. By the way, that idea of נאמנת עלי *ne'emenes alai*
is very powerful because right now there's been some ideas about dealing
with some ways of dealing with עגונה *agunah* issue and certain types
of a pre-nuptial agreement that make certain conditions or whatever and the
question always is well what happens if the husband contests what happened
or what if the husband says that he changed the conditions? So
one of the things that's put in is says and my wife
is believed more than a hundred witnesses to claim what did or
did not happen. So it's helpful because then it also addresses the
lack of knowledge or any counter-claims. So anyway, so that's what he
says. No matter what I claim, no matter what happens, she's believed
to say that I didn't return. But otherwise we'd be concerned that
maybe he returned. So that's a case he put it on hold
and if there's not a special circumstances of believing her, we're concerned
that he might have returned. So here too when he told the
שליח shliach *shliach* hold it for thirty days, let's be concerned that
he might have returned unless it's a special case where he said
she should be believed, but nobody said that that was the case.
So why aren't we concerned? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says איכסוף *ichsof*, so he was embarrassed. דקא *daka*,
a lot of being embarrassed, a lot of showing people up that
we had yesterday too. That's a good point, why aren't we concerned
about that? He didn't have an answer. ולסוף איגלאי מילתא דארוסה הויא
*u'lesof iglaei milsa de'arusa havaya*, then it turned out that the woman
he was divorcing was only an ארוסה *arusa*. So if it's an
ארוסה *arusa*, they've never been together, they've never been living together, we're
not afraid, A, that the likelihood of reconciling I guess is less,
they never really ever lived together as a married couple, and B,
the likelihood of actually like being in ייחוד *yichud* and maybe having
sex is less. אמר רבא Amar Rava, *amar Rava*, אם אמרו בנשואה
*im amru be'nesuah*, if they had this concern about reconciling in the
case of
a נשואה *nesuah*, יאמרו בארוסה *yomru be'arusa*, would they say it by
an ארוסה *arusa*? Okay, so anyway, so he
that was like a... So that's actually interesting, right? That if somebody
explicitly puts it on hold, do we have to be concerned with
lack of evidence that there was a problem, do we have to
concern that maybe they reconciled? Okay, that raises a lot, that makes
things a big issue, right? You always have to be concerned if
you had the ability to come back, maybe he did. Yes, Charlie?
Wait, wait, Charlie had a question. He was embarrassed, the one who
פסק that it was okay was embarrassed, that was רבא. Rava. No,
רב הונא. No, רבא. Rava. Yes, רבא Rava who said it's okay,
we'll take care of it. How could he take care of it?
How do we know what happened within the last 30 days?
You mentioned postdated checks a few minutes ago. That whether postdated checks
are valid before the date depends on the country. And it turns
out in the United States they are. Oh, really? Yes, if the
bank cashes your postdated check, you probably,
unless you've informed the bank not
to. Okay, I'm surprised, I just looked it up right now.
Very interesting. Always a font of knowledge, Charlie.
אמר רבא, Rava. הבא דקא מיבעיא לן. hava deka mibaya lan. So
now back to רבא. Rava So רבא said, okay, this is, but
this question I, here's the question I have. So we just introduced
some interesting idea of שליח שלא ניתן לגירושין. shliach shelo nitan leigerushin.
You need to have, be empowered to give the גט in order
to hand it over to בית דין. Beis Din. And the idea
that what do you call it of that,
and the idea
that if it was put on hold, we might have to be
concerned that he came back and he reconciled. So גמרא Gemara says,
but here's my question. הבא דקא מיבעיא לן. hava deka mibaya lan.
כי משוי בי דינא שליח בפניו ושלא בפניו. ki mshavi bei dina
shliach befanav v'shelo befanav. When בית דין Beis Din makes a שליח
shliach to replace the original שליח, shliach it's the powers now been
given over to them, does the first שליח shliach have to be
present? Because we've already established, right? That this guy is a, when
the בית דין Beis Din makes it... well let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara הדר פשטה. hadar pashata. Then he said, בין
בפניו בין שלא בפניו. bein befanav bein shelo befanav. Whether in his
presence or not. שלח מתם, shlach matam, בין בפניו בין שלא בפניו.
bein befanav bein shelo befanav. Now, which makes a lot of sense,
because if you'll remember, the גמרא Gemara basically said that if the
first שליח shliach died, you know, it doesn't matter. They're not really
the שליח shliach of the שליח, shliach they're the שליח shliach of
the husband or to some degree they're maybe a שליח shliach, of
בית דין Beis Din depending if it was ארץ ישראל or חוץ
לארץ. Okay,
but you don't so if it maybe it was a שליח shliach
of the שליח shaliach you might need the first שליח to be
present to demonstrate somehow the official transfer. Okay, but that's not true,
it's a שליח fundamentally they're a שליח of the husband and certainly
in the בית דין Beis Din case the שליח gives over to
the בית דין Beis Din and the בית דין Beis Din gives
over to the next שליח, so all the more reason why you
do not need the first שליח to be present. Okay, now because
we mentioned this idea of if I return within 12 months, we're
going to have a little bit of a digression and a self-contained
סוגיא sugya that appears in כתובות Kesuvos and elsewhere. ההוא דאמר. hahu
de'amar. There was a man who said, אילו לא אתינא תלתין יומי,
ilu lo ateina taltin yomei, if I don't return within 30 days,
ליהוי גיטא, leihavei gita, let the גט be valid. אתא, ata, he
came back after 30 days... before 30 days were up, ופסקה מברא.
upaska mabara. But there was a, there was a river that was
separated and he couldn't come back. Okay, the whatever there was a,
you know, the river, the banks were very high, he couldn't find
a, you know, some type of a way to get over the
river. Okay, אמר להו. amar lehu. So
but he you know and the clock was running out so he
yelled to the other side of the river חזו דאתאי חזו דאתאי,
chazu de'atai chazu de'atai, look look I'm here I'm trying to come,
I'm coming, I'm coming, I'm coming. So אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, so
therefore and he wanted the גט to be annulled because he wanted
the תנאי tnai to be considered satisfied. I mean, yeah... but
I always get confused because it's in the negative. If I don't
come... he wanted to be annulled. Anyway,
he wanted the תנאי tnai to be not satisfied and the גט
to be void. Anyway, okay, so anyway he wanted the גט to
be annulled but but he wasn't actually returned. So אמר שמואל, amar
Shmuel, לא שמיה מתיא. lo shmei matya. It's very nice that he's
yelling, he hasn't come back. Okay, so the גט is now valid.
Now this is a סוגיא sugya that's discussed in כתובות Kesuvos which
is called יש אונס בגיטין או אין אונס בגיטין. yesh ones begittin
o ein ones begittin. Okay, which means when people make conditions, right?
So okay, it's very nice what שמואל Shmuel saying is, you wanted
to have come back, but bottom line is the condition wasn't met,
you didn't come back. Okay,
so that's the normal way to say it. Now what's the argument
to say that the fact that it's out of your hands and
you're crying shouldn't matter, should make it different? Because what we basically
say is we try to say, well bottom line is, you know,
you are the one who made the stipulation. So, you know, you
could say look I never meant for it to apply to a
case when I was trying and something was making me unable to
come back, but what I meant was if I'm willingly choosing not
to come back, right? I didn't mean this case. Okay, so how
much is we probably didn't mean this situation, but you didn't say
it. And הלכה halacha has to go with what you said, and
if you wanted to say something more nuanced, then you should have
told us that. So that's the issue. שמואל Shmuel said, I don't
care what you're thinking now, I don't care what you were thinking
when you made the תנאי, tnai, you said if I don't come
back.
Okay, exactly.
And she maybe
she's good, she maybe she's waiting, waiting to she'll marry the the
other guy. Okay, anyway. Okay, ההוא גברא דאמר להו, Hahu gavra d'amar
lehu, so man said to witnesses, אי לא פייסנא לה תלתין יומין
ליהוי גיטא. Ee lo paisna lah tlasi yomin lehave gita. If I
don't reconcile with her, that's what we're quoting this about reconciling, right,
within thirty days let it be valid. אזל פייסה ולא איפייסה. Aza
pisa velo ipisa.
He went to try to reconcile with her and she wasn't having
anything of it. So basically he tried. So
but alright, it's you know, it's like trying only gets an A
for effort, only gets you so far. אמר רב יוסף מי יהיב
לה תיקרא תרקבא דדינרי ולא פייסה? Amar Rav Yosef mi yaiv lah
tikra tarkava de-dinari velo paisa?
Did he try to give her a basket filled with gold coins
and she didn't agree? Meaning, you know, try a little harder. Did
he send her flowers? Did he send her whatever? It's funny that
they make it so financial. But the bottom line is, it's like
I don't care that you tried. You try harder. You know, now
of course what תוספות Tosafot asks is the real point should be
I don't care if you did give her a basket filled with
gold coins, you still didn't reconcile. Okay? But either way, the point
is like you didn't satisfy the condition. End of story. All right,
so that's your טענת אונס, tayna de-onus, I tried, is not valid.
Either it's not a real אונס, onus, you didn't try hard enough,
or it doesn't really matter. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say, אמר
רב יוסף מידי תרקבא דדינרי בעיא ומיהבא לה? Amar Rav Yosef midi
tarkava de-dinari baia u-maihava lah? What, you think he has to give
her a basket full of gold coins? So meaning he's actually saying
the opposite opinion. He's saying he tried and that counts. Okay. What
he meant when he said if I don't make up with her,
he assumed, you know, oh of course, if I want to make
up with her she'll be okay with it. So what he meant
was if I don't try to make up with her. And therefore
even though he didn't do what he actually said, but we go
by what he meant, not by what he said. Okay, and that's
the question. When somebody says if X, do they need to exclude
cases when they're trying and not succeeding? And that's this debate of
יש אונס בגיטין yesh onus be-gitin or not. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara ends with כד כמאן דאמר יש אונס בגיטין הא כמאן
דאמר אין אונס בגיטין. kad keman de-amar yesh onus be-gitin ha keman
de-amar ein onus be-gitin. Okay, if you say יש אונס בגיטין, yesh
onus be-gitin, it means saying I tried, I tried, you know, is
a good claim and we say when you make your condition you
mean not only if I don't do this or if I, but
you know, if I do this but you know if I try
to and I'm trying to do this that it also counts. That's
what you mean. That's יש אונס בגיטין. yesh onus be-gitin. Or do
we say אין אונס בגיטין. ein onus be-gitin. No, I don't care
whether you tried. When you said X, then it has to be
X. All right. So that's a whole סוגיא sugya in כתובות. Ketubot.
We won't go more into depth about it here. Let's look at
the next
משנה. Mishnah המלווה מעות את הכהן ואת הלוי ואת העני היו מפריש
עליהם מחלקן מפריש עליהם בחזקת שהן קיימין. Hamalveh maot et hakohen ve-et
halevi ve-et he-ani hayu mafrish aleihen mechalkan mafrish aleihen bechezkat shehen kayamim.
So you might ask what does this have to do with גיטין?
Gittin? And the answer is nothing. But we are going back to
a משנה Mishnah about the שליח who left the husband and delivered
the גט with the presumption that the husband was still alive. And
now we're going to do about similar scenarios where somebody isn't around
and can act with the presumption that the person is still alive.
And by the way, I should just warn you that we are
about to turn to a, at the end of this פרק, perek,
we'll have similar types of scenarios about having nothing to do with
גיטין, Gittin, presuming a person is still alive. And then we are
actually building up to the next פרק, perek, which is going to
open with a גט case, but introduce a concept of תיקון עולם,
Tikkun Olam, and then we're going to have two full פרקים prakim
of things that have nothing to do with גיטין, Gittin, but have
to do with general ideas like תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. Okay, so
it's going to be nice, this is an interesting middle section of
גיטין Gittin that is like a nice collection of a wide range
of different things, you know, all that somehow we digress to talk
about. Okay, so here's the case here. Case is that
a certain כהן kohen in town needs to borrow money. Okay, or
a certain לוי Levi or a certain poor person. I lend him
money. Okay, but you know, I'm actually a little bit afraid about
whether he's going to be able to pay me back or whatever.
But I got it all worked out. You know why? Because I'm
a farmer, and after the crops come in, what I'll do is
the following: I'll say to the כהן, kohen,
okay, I'll lend you money, and what we'll do is when it
comes time for giving תרומה, terumah, I'll give it to you and
you'll pay me back with that תרומה terumah that I'll give you.
See it? So I'm going to get back the grain I would
have had to have given another כהן, kohen, I'll give it to
him, I'll get it back. So I'll get my loan paid off.
Okay, that's what we're going to do. But actually, let's do it
even simpler. Why do I have to give it to you and
you give it back to me? I'll just separate the תרומה terumah
and I'll just pocket it after I've separated it. Now of course,
I can't eat it if I'm not a כהן, kohen, I could
sell it to another כהן, kohen, but like I don't have to
actually physically deliver it to you and have you deliver it back
to me. I'll just hold on to it in payment for for,
you know, for the debt. Or for the לוי, Levi, I won't
give you, I'll separate off the מעשר ma'aser so the grain isn't
טבל, tevel, and then I'll just keep it because I can eat
מעשר, ma'aser, and that'll be payment for the debt. Or if it's
מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, same thing, I'll separate off מעשר עני ma'aser
ani and I'll keep it for payment for the debt. And we
make this agreement. Okay, so the הלכה halacha is
המלווה מעות את הכהן. Hamalveh maot et hakohen. and I'm going to
separate off the money from their portion, meaning that I'll be מפריש
Mafrish *maphrish* the תרומות trumos, *Terumos* and מעשרות *Maastros* and then that
for them and then I'll keep it to payments of the debt.
So מפריש עליהם בחזקת שהם קיימים *maphrish aleihem bechezkat sheheim kayamim*, and
I can even
I don't have to have them present, I can assume that they're
still alive, okay, and ואינו חושש שמא מת הכהן או הלוי או
העני או שהעשיר העני *veino choshesh shema meis hakohen o halevi o
heani o sheheeshir heani*. I don't be I'm not afraid that the
Cohen or Levi died or the Ani died or the Ani got
rich. If the Ani got rich I can't give him מעשר עני
ma'aser ani *Maaser Ani*. So I can assume though that when I'm
מפריש *maphrish* it I'm still saying this is for that Cohen and
I'm going to now come back and pocket it. Because if he's
not alive, right, I can't give him תרומה truma, *Terumah* if he's
not alive. I can't give him מעשר Ma'aser *Maaser* if he's not
alive. So how can I say I gave it to him and
now it's paid back to me? I haven't given תרומות ומעשרות Terumos
u-ma'asros, *Terumos u'maastros*. But I can go ahead and I can assume
that he's still alive, similar to giving the גט *Get* and assuming
the husband is still alive. Okay now מתו *meisu*, let's say they
actually did die and I know they died. Now what do I
do? This dead Cohen owed me a hundred dollars, okay, and I
have a hundred dollars worth of תרומה truma. *Terumah* here. All right?
Is there any way I can use this to pay up my
debt? Okay so well here's the question: does anybody now, let's start
with this, does anybody now still owe me the hundred dollars once
he died? So you would assume who might still owe me the
hundred dollars? The יורשים *yorshim*, the heirs. If he had actually קרקע
karka. *karka*, heirs are not obligated with debts if there are no
liens on the property. Okay so they don't actually assume the personal
obligations of their father. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מצוה על היורשים
לפרוע חוב אביהם *mitzvah al hayorshim liproa chov avihem*, there's a מצוה
*mitzvah* for them to assume the debts of their father, but it's
not really a personal, they really are not personally indebted. But if
I have a lien on the property, right, I mean I think
that you know then that lien then that property when they inherit
it I still have rights to that property. Okay so if basically
let's in the case let's say that I do have a lien
on the property for the Cohen, okay, although that's unlikely here because
it wasn't like a it wasn't didn't seem that it was with
a שטר חוב *shtar chov*, it seemed like it was an oral
agreement, probably wouldn't have
entailed liens on the property, right, then I could work out an
arrangement where I could give it to the יורשים *yorshim* and then
I'll say to them rather than me taking your property here's the
here's the hundred dollars of תרומה terumah. *Terumah* and I'll just now
pocket the תרומה terumah *Terumah*. So it could work with the יורשים
*yorshim*, but they would a, have to agree to do that exchange,
okay, they didn't make the original agreement, and right, so but in
theory it could work. That's when there's a lien on the property.
If there's no lien on the property, then I'm stuck. I had
a hundred dollars of תרומה terumah. *Terumah* that I would have liked
to have pocketed, okay, but nobody owes me the money anymore. He
died, I didn't have a lien on his property. Either he didn't
have property or maybe this case doesn't have liens altogether for the
reason I just said, that there was no שטר *shtar*, it was
all oral, okay, so I'm never going to get so I'm now
going to have to find some other Cohen to give this תרומה
terumah *Terumah* to and I'm not going to get my debt paid
off. But the משנה *mishna* says no. If well yes but מתו
צריך ליטול רשות מן היורשים *meisu tzorich litol reshus min hayorshim*. If
the heirs agree you can still pocket the תרומה *Terumah*. So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* understands that what that means is there was no property,
there was no I had no liens, so I have no legal
right to to collect the the debt is technically no longer around,
I have no legal right to keep the תרומה *Terumah*. But as
we said יורשים *yorshim* have a מצוה *mitzvah* to satisfy their father's
you know debts. So if the they agree they say look technically
you don't legally owe me the money or you have a מצוה
*mitzvah* to do it and guess what I made this arrangement with
your father. If you're okay with it we'll keep the arrangement with
you guys and I'll just keep pocket the money myself. And if
they say fine that's good then it works because it's like I
virtually gave the תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-maasros, *terumos u'maastros* to the heirs—they're
also כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* and לויים Levi'im *levi'im*—and they gave it back
to me. So we transfer the arrangement with the father to the
heirs. The reason I need their permission is I need their permission
to transfer the arrangement, but I first need their agreement that they're
willing to pay off their father's debts. If you kids are willing
to pay off your father's debts, which you're not legally obligated to
do, but if you're willing to do it I got a great
way to make it happen. We had this arrangement, are you okay
with this arrangement? Sure fine whatever we don't know what you're talking
about keep the תרומות ומעשרות *terumos u'maastros*. And so he keeps it
and it's good. Okay then that works. All right the problem now
the same would also be true with an עני ani *ani* in
theory, okay, but except if the kids aren't עניים aniyim *aniyim* that
might make it a little more difficult. Anyway אם הלוון בפני בית
דין beis din *im hilvan bifnei beis din* and now we're also
introducing the role of בית דין beis din *beis din* like we
did by the שליח *shaliach*, so that's another way this is relevant,
אינו צריך ליטול רשות מן היורשים *eino tzorich litol reshus min hayorshim*.
So if we I made this arrangement with the original כהן kohen.
*cohen* לוי *levi* or the עני ani *ani* in front of בית
דין beis din *beis din*, then the בית דין beis din *beis
din* can assume somehow that responsibility and play a role sort of
like making us beginning to think of like פרוזבול *prozbul* and those
types of things which we're going to get into in גיטין *Gittin*,
and בית דין beis din *beis din* can basically say we're going
to say that that's what's going to happen. We're going to say
in this case you know we somehow we you know בית דין
beis din *beis din* has control over דיני ממונות *dinei mammonos* and
we're going to say that the heirs are going to pay up
the debt and that the arrangement applies to the heirs as well.
Okay, so now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
ואף על גב דלא אתו לידי *Veaf al gav de lo asu
leyadei*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute. I don't get how
this arrangement works. How can you pocket, you separated off תרומות ומעשרות
*trumos umasros*, and now you're going to pocket it for the debt.
But you never gave it to the כהן kohen *kohen* or the
לוי *Levi*. So, how does that כהן kohen *kohen* or לוי *Levi*
own it to pay it back to you? And there's a double
question here. One question is a simple דיני ממונות *dinei mamonos* question.
This money right now can be given to any כהן kohen *kohen*,
any לוי *Levi*. How does this particular כהן kohen *kohen* or לוי
*Levi* own it that I can now take it back in payment
of my debt? That's question number one. Question number two is, there's
a מצוה *mitzvah* to give it to a כהן kohen *kohen* or
a לוי *Levi*, not just to separate it. When did I ever
do that מצוה *mitzvah* of delivering it? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* mentions
both. Look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. ואף על גב דלא אתו לידי
*Veaf al gav de lo asu leyadei*, רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* says בתמיה
אף על פי שאינו נותן לכהן ויחזירם לו קתני מתניתין דאפרש להו
*bitmiya af al pi sheino nosen lakohen veyachzirem lo katni masnisin deafresh
lehu*. How can you do that? דכיון דלא מטו לידי *decheivan delo
matu leyadei*, if it never came to the כהן kohen *kohen*, מאן
זכי ליה להאי כהן kohen, *man zachye lei lehai kohen*? הך תרומה
שיקבלנה זה בחובו *hach truma sheyekabelna ze bechovo*. How did this particular
כהן kohen *kohen* ever get ownership over this? Right, this could go
to any כהן *kohen*. And number two is, היכא יצא ידי נתינה
*heicha yatza yedei nesina*, right? And that, you know, I want רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* really to say there's another point. You didn't ever do
your מצוה *mitzvah* of giving it to a כהן *kohen*. So how
did you just do it, separate it and put it in your
pocket? Where's the, where did you give it to the כהן *kohen*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב *Amar Rav*, במכירי כהונה
ולויה *bemakirei kehuna uleviya*. We're talking about families that are basically, you
know, you know this family well and you have an established practice
of giving to this family. Okay, this was actually a particular institution.
I mean the problem would be, you know, if it was let's
say a powerful family or whatever, it wasn't like, you know, that
everybody gave their תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*, you know, to this particular
family. But there were cases like that that there were people that,
you know, you had a practice of always giving. You were good
friends with the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* down the street, and for generations,
your family has been giving its תרומה *truma* to the כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim*, and it's been giving its מעשרות *masros* to the סגלים *Segals*
two blocks over. Now, those are כהן *kohen* and לוי *Levi* names,
right? Even though סגל *Segal* is סגן לכהונה *Sgan LaKehuna*, right? סגלים
*Segals* tend to be לוויים *Leviyim*. Okay, anyway, so, or it could
be לוי *Levi*. לוי *Levi* is a last name too. Anyway, so
you have the practice, you've been doing it for generations. In that
type of a case, somehow it's assumed that even without, it's a
little unclear how the mechanics work, but it's assumed that even without
an act of giving it to them, the very separating of your
תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*, because that pattern has been well-established, makes it
like they automatically take possession of it. Okay, so that's a special
circumstance. ושמואל אמר *Ushmuel amar*, במזכה להם על ידי אחרים *bemizakeh lahem
al yedei acheirim*. ושמואל *Shmuel* says, no no no, it'll be, I
just call over my friend. I says, look, I got this whole
deal with this כהן *kohen* or with this לוי *Levi*. Here, take
this תרומה *truma* for the כהן *kohen* and then and give it
back to me. They say fine, whatever, and you take it and
you give it back to me. Okay, so you use a third
party to take possession for the כהן *kohen* and לוי *Levi* and
the עני ani *ani*, and then and then they hand it back
to you and you have your debt paid back.
And then they say why is that better than just go bring
it to them? And that's more convenient.
It's more convenient. They live halfway, right? I said down the block.
But you know they, I don't know, they're halfway across town. Okay,
I just, okay. So, עולא אמר *Ulla amar*, הא מני רבי יוסי
היא *ha mani Rabbi Yossi hi*. This is רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*
דאמר עשו את שאינו זוכה כזוכה *deamar asu es sheino zocheh kezocheh*.
He basically said this is rabbinic. The rabbis, you're right, technically the
כהן *kohen* לוי *Levi* and עני ani *ani* they don't own it.
The rabbis made it like they did own it in order to
enable this system to work. And here we're going to introduce an
idea which we're going to see in a minute, that it's in
everybody's interest, well, certainly in the כהן *kohen* לוויים *Leviyim* and the
עניים aniyim *aniyim*'s interest to have this system work. Who wouldn't want
to borrow money and never have to pay it back? Right? I
borrowed the money and all I'm going to have to pay back
is the תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros* he's going to give me later
which he might not even have given me if he didn't lend
me the money. You understand? It's a really good deal. Right? I'm
going to borrow money and you're going to agree that I'm going
to be the recipient of the תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros* you'll give
later and then you'll take it back. Fine, great. All I know
is it's free money. Okay, so accordingly כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* לוויים *Leviyim*
and the עניים aniyim. *aniyim* love this arrangement. It's good for them.
Maybe it lets me be a צדיק *tzadik* and lend money to
people and also pretty confident that I'm going to get my loan
paid back. So sort of like everybody wins. Okay, so therefore, in
order to make this institution work, חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* greased the wheels.
And they said and we're going to make it easy and you
don't even have to have the כהן *kohen* and לוי *Levi* and
the עני ani *ani* around. You know, you separate it, it's like
they take possession of it and you put it back in your
pocket. Okay, how that exactly works, you know, חז"ל *Chazal* have some
control over דיני ממונות *dinei mamonos*. They can sort of make things
happen. Yes.
What if he has no produce in a future circumstance? He loses
his field or whatever. What?
Yeah, the גמרא *Gemara* is going to deal with that. Then he's
out his money. He's out his money. Okay, which is why it's
really good for the כהן *kohen* לוי *Levi* and the עני ani
*ani*. Okay? 'Cause if there was a blight or whatever and then
then he only can be paid back with the תרומות ומעשרות *trumos
umasros*. That's the arrangement. Yes. Of this year, of this year.
Is there any requirement that טבל *tevel* that he's eventually going to
separate actually exist?
'Cause this, yeah, you have to separate to get rid
of
the
טבל *tevel*.
But they don't own it yet. When I separate it, then they'll
own it and then I'll put it back in my pocket because
then you'll have to pay me back.
Right, but he's made an agreement to pay back with something that
doesn't exist yet.
Okay, but he's not selling it as doesn't exist. He's just going
to pay, it's a way you're going to pay back a loan.
That's not a problem. Okay, when you borrow money you don't have
money now, you're promising to pay back with money you don't have
right now. Okay, so anyways the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
Okay. So now, כולהו כרב לא אמרי *Kulehu kerav lo amri*, people
didn't say it was רב *Rav*, a case of an established family,
במכירא לא תני *bimchira lo tani*, that's not in the משנה *Mishnah*.
We so we'd rather not insert things in the משנה *Mishnah* that
aren't there. כשמואל לא אמרי *Kishmuel lo amri*, they didn't say like
שמואל *Shmuel* that you've got a third party to take possession, במזכה
לא תני *bimzakeh lo tani*, that's also not in the משנה *Mishnah*.
Now כעולא נמי לא אמרי *Ke-Ulla nami lo amri*, why not like
עולא *Ulla*? Because who quoted like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*, which seems
to be the best explanation that חז"ל *Chazal* just made this whole
institution work. ביחידא לא מוקמינן *Byechida lo mokminan*, we'd rather the משנה
*Mishnah* not go like a דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*. Okay, but those
are different ways of explaining how the other side takes possession. One
way or another, the other side took possession.
How it is, it's just thirty pages into גיטין *Gittin* from the
beginning of ש"ס *Shas*, all of a sudden they come up with
a פשט *pshat* that they don't want to insert anything that's not
in the משנה *Mishnah*?
Yeah, that's why, you know, obviously very often we do, but the
point is that's why people would prefer one answer as opposed to
another answer. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan *Tanu rabanan*, המלווה מעות את הכהן
ואת הלוי ואת העני להיות מפריש עליהן מחלקן *Hamalveh ma'ot et ha-Kohen
ve'et ha-Levi ve'et ha-Ani lihyot mafrish aleihen mechalkan*, so a ברייתא *braita*
that starts saying you have the same arrangement, מפריש עליהם בחזקת שהן
קיימין *mafrish aleihem bechezkas she-hen kayamin*, you go ahead and you do
it, you separate it and you pocket it assuming they're still alive,
ופוסק עמהן כשער הזול *ufosek imahen kesha'ar hazol*. And now here's the
question: how much, what is the rate of, that I'm going to
we're going to figure out the value of the wheat for? All
right? So I let's say, you know, you borrowed a hundred dollars
and the value of the wheat ranges from one to two dollars
per bushel. Okay? How many, so how many bushels of wheat are
we talking about? Are we talking about a hundred or are we
talking about fifty? Okay? So I can stipulate and say the debt
is going to be paid off at the lowest market rate for
you know, for the wheat, at one dollar a bushel, which means
that a hundred bushels I would have had to give to some
other לוי *Levi* and now I'm going to basically give it to
you and then keep it. Okay? Which by the way means also
and that's going to be the next line, ואין בו משום ריבית
Ve-ein bo mishum ribbis. *ve-ein bo mishum ribbit*. You can actually see
how I can wind up making money from this deal, right? Because
I would have had to give a hundred bushels to another לוי
*Levi*, ah, and at that stage it might have been worth two
hundred dollars. But I'm going to lend you a hundred dollars and
pocket a hundred bushels later, so I might have actually saved myself
some money in that whole exchange. All right? So that you're allowed
to do. Okay? Which yes.
What's what's the general הלכה *halacha* in terms of the שער Sha'ar.
*sha'ar*?
So the גמרא *Gemara* is going to ask that. Because actually there
are cases where you can if you pre-sell food and there is
a known, you know, you can't make be stipulate to go by
the lower שער *sha'ar*. So how much do we look at these
things as loans or as sales? But but anyway, so the גמרא
*Gemara* will see that, okay? That's a whole סוגיא *sugya* in בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia *Bava Metzia*. So we're just going to skim the
surface of it. Exactly. Okay, ואין בו משום ריבית Ribbis *ve-ein bo
mishum ribbit*, and there's not a ריבית Ribbis *ribbit* concern and as
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says is תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafot* takes this even further.
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says not only that, you can even agree on
an exchange rate that is far below the normal exchange rate. Meaning
not just we'll say whatever the rate is over the course of
the summer, we'll take the lowest amount. That would be שער הזול
*sha'ar hazol*. Okay? You could actually say, you could set an exchange
rate that is lower than normal than it ever normally would be
and that and that's also a problem and it's not a ריבית
Ribbis *ribbit* problem. Okay? So חז"ל *Chazal* made it they really like
stretched the law here in order to make this institution work. And
you gotta think about it, everybody benefits. I benefit that I don't
have to give so much תרומות ומעשרות *Terumot u-Maasrot*. I get to
keep more than I would have given away. Okay? If I can
make if I can agree on a low exchange rate. And the
עניים aniyim. *Aniyim* and לויים *Leviyim* and they all benefit that they
get to pre-borrow money on their futures, on the you know, the
future type of of stuff that they would have and they might
not have gotten personally anyway. So everybody really wins. Yes.
Were there a lot of poor כהנים *Kohanim* to
Probably, I'm sure there were.
I'm sure there were probably some very wealthy
families, like you know, and I'm sure that a lot of them
were very poor. Absolutely. Okay.
You keep some percentage, even a big percentage of that תרומה *Terumah*,
right? So but you still it's still תרומה *Terumah*, you can't eat
it,
you have to sell it. Right, you had to, in the תרומה
*Terumah* case you have to sell it to another כהן *Kohen*. Right.
Okay. ואין שביעית משמטתו ve-ein sheviis meshamtetto, *Ve-ein Shevi'it meshamtatto*. Now if
שמיטה *Shmita* comes in the middle here, it does not annul it,
because it's not like a we'll see why, because
basically because שמיטה *Shmita* only works if I can like it starts
with I shouldn't pressure you to pay my debt and I have
an actual like claim on you. But in this case the borrower
is out of the picture. He borrowed his money and I never
see him again. So since I don't have like a claim on
him and I can't pressure him to pay a debt, it actually
means that the debt doesn't get annulled, okay, because I'm basically just
going to pay myself. Okay? ואם בא לחזור אינו חוזר, ve-im ba
lachazor eino chozer, but how
and if you want to retract you can't retract. נתייאשו הבעלים. Nityashu
ha-be'alim. Who is that? What's that?
Who wants to retract? Okay, so the הגמרא Ha-gemara is going to
discuss which side are we talking about. Okay, presumably we're talking about
the בעל הבית Ba'al ha-bayis because he's the one we've been focusing
on, but the הגמרא Ha-gemara will discuss that. Okay. ואם בא נתייאשו
הבעלים אין מפרישין עליהם. Ve-im ba nityashu ha-be'alim ein mafrishin aleihem.
Now let's say it looks like there's a that you know there's
a big infestation and I'm saying to myself that's it, the whole
crop is going to waste and I guess I'm never going to
get that debt paid back. Okay? Of course that's the that's the
last thing on your mind if your whole crop is going to
waste. But anyway, but so if you once you give up hope
of getting that debt paid back from the crop, then even if
the crop improved you basically have now forfeited the debt and you
can't get it paid back, which is very strange. Okay? אין מפרישין
עליהם. Ein mafrishin aleihem. מפני שהוא מפריש על האבוד. Mipnei she-hu mafrish
al ha-avud. Once you have given it up then you can no
it's you cannot go ahead and be מפריש as a way of
paying back the debt. It's not clear why, that's supposed to be
explanatory, but I still don't understand why not. יאוש. Ye'ush. I understand.
But if I think if you owe me a thousand dollars and
then you've absconded somewhere, whatever, and I say that's it you know
he's never going to I'm never going to find him. I don't
lose you don't stop owing me the money, right? So you don't.
No, this has very much to do with the fact that specifically
there's a concrete object which I was going to get paid back
with and it's like I gave up ownership of that object. That's
what it is. It's not I gave up hope of you paying
me back, it's that your payment was right here in front of
me and I go that's it, it's lost. I'm like מתייאש Mityayesh
on that. But the funny thing is I still do own my
own crop, you know? It's not like I stop owning my crop.
יאוש Ye'ush of אבוד.
Avud.
Yeah, exactly, exactly. Yeah. Okay. I assume that there was
something in loans laws generally that if you מתייאש Mityayesh you no,
but you don't.
Yeah, so it's special to this case. Okay. Although this this worked
out to say it's almost like saying up in smoke.
יאוש, Ye'ush, אש. Eish. אש, Eish, smoke.
Yeah,
that's interesting. I don't think that's what it's from, but okay. All
right, let's take a look. All right, so הגמרא Ha-gemara says like
this. אמר מר. Amar mar.
So now we're going to attack this a little bit. פוסקין עמהן
כשר הזול. Poskin imahen ke-sha'ar ha-zol. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously. Now the reason
it says obviously, why is it so obvious, is because there's a
משנה in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that says you're allowed to do
this. However, the problem with the משנה in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia.
is you're allowed to do this when you're actually selling wheat. I
can sell you like wheat based on the שער. And by the
way, it might actually have to be that I actually have the
wheat in my possession and so on. But anyway, but then I
can sell it to you and then even if it winds up
that I'm delivering more than you paid me for, it's not real
ריבית ribis. because we're talking about a sale, we're not talking about
a loan, right? You get it? I'm selling you a hundred bushels
of wheat, we determine what the exchange rate is, we can decide
a low exchange rate. Okay, I was still figuring out that I'm
going to make a profit somehow, I got a special supplier. And
then if the rates change and you wind up winning in the
deal, it's you know, it's not real ריבית because it was a
sale that I lost out on. Okay, but that's but that's so
that's that this is not this case. This actually is a is
a loan. But the הגמרא Ha-gemara seems to be willing to consider
it as like a pre-sale. I'm going to give you this hundred
dollars and maybe that's also why there's an idea of יאוש. Ye'ush.
It's anyway, I'm going to give you this hundred dollars and it's
like you're pre-purchasing your own, I don't anyway, or I am pre-purchasing
your own מעשר that you're going to get later. Anyway, so the
הגמרא Ha-gemara somehow says it's obvious you should be able to set
a low a low exchange rate. פשיטא. Peshita. Because that's the principle
we have by by transactions in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia, So the
הגמרא Ha-gemara says where am I? הא קמשמע לן אף על פי
שלא פסק כמי שפסק דמי. Ha kamashma lan af al pi she-lo
pasak kemi she-pasak dami. No, it just the חידוש Chidush is that
we presume that that's the case. Okay? And again, this is in
everybody's best interest. It makes me want to do this, me the
בעל הבית. Ba'al ha-bayis. So we're going to take for a standard
presumption that when you lend the money and you say we're going
to do it, you'll pay me back with your תרומות ומעשרות, that
it means based on the lowest exchange rate, the one that's most
in my favor. And that's just presumed. Okay. ואין בו משום ריבית.
And there's not a ריבית concern either in this case or just,
תוספות Tosafos reads it as even if you set a lower rate.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not? כיון דכי לית ליה לא יהיב
ליה. Keivan de-ki leis lei lo yahiv lei. Since
it's because it's not a normal loan. And this maybe makes it
more like I was saying before, like that case in בבא מציעא,
Bava Metzia. it makes it more like a pre-sale. What makes it
more like a pre-sale? Because if the crop is destroyed and there's
nothing to be paid back, you're not going to have to pay
me back the loan. Right? You get that? If it was a
real loan, how did you stop having to pay me back? Okay,
but the fact that if there's no crop you are free from
paying me back means that to some degree it's more like a
pre-sale than it is a loan. Okay? And therefore, כיון דכי לית
ליה, Keivan de-ki leis lei, if I don't have a... not give
it to me, so it's not really so much of a loan.
So כי אית ליה נמי, ki islei nami, so if there is
a nice crop, אין בו משום ריבית, ein bo mishum ribis, and
I wind up keeping more, you know, more that's worth a lot
more than the money I lent you because we set a very
low exchange rate, that's not really ריבית. We're looking at it as
more of a sale and less of a loan and that allows
us to me to set a very low exchange rate. Yes.
I mean, is this similar? Like, I, I, I buy something from
a factory and the buyer in the factory, the thing I bought
burns up. Right. Does that mean they don't have to refund my
money if I've already pre-paid?
Well, they do whatever because that gets...
technically, right, that would be שייך shayach to this type of deliber...
Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, that is true, yes. Yes.
Okay, that'll lot depends about משיכה meshicha and חצר chatzer and מקומות,
mekomos, but yes. Okay. And are they a שומר shomer or not
a שומר? shomer? Okay. But anyway, but the basic point here is
we're allowed to do this and it makes it in the בעל
הבית'ס baal habayis's best interest. He's assumed to be a very low
exchange rate, he can set an even lower one according to תוספות.
Tosafos Does that make me want to do it? That makes you
benefit and we're basically seeing it like an early, like a pre-sale
of the תרומות ומעשרות, pre-purchase.
Okay. Now, ואין שביעית sheviis משמטתו,
and שביעית sheviis doesn't annul it, ולא קרינן ביה ve-lo karinan bei
לא יגוש lo yigosh because שביעית sheviis only annuls debts that are
relevant to the prohibition of don't oppress, like don't, you know, or
don't press your, you know, the borrower for repayment. But there's no
pressing of the borrower, he's out of the picture now. ואם בא
לחזור אינו חוזר, now you can't retract. So here is Jenna's question:
אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa לא שנו אלא בבעל הבית, lo
shanu ela be-baal habayis, the בעל הבית baal habayis can't retract from
the כהן. Again, a lot of things are in the interest of
the כהן here, not everything. The fact that שביעית doesn't משמט meshamet
protects the בעל הבית. baal habayis. Anyway, but the בעל הבית baal
habayis can't retract, אבל כהן בבעל הבית aval kohen be-baal habayis אם
בא לחזור חוזר. im ba lachazor chozer. But the כהן can retract.
Why? תנן, נתן לו מעות ולא משך הימנו פירות יכול לחזור בו.
nasan lo maos ve-lo mashach heimenu peiros yachol lachazor bo. In a
normal case of a transaction, actually this is similar to Dov's question,
if I pay for the pay for something but I've not yet
taken possession of the object, I can go back on the sale.
That's a normal sale. Okay. So the גמרא says this is like
a little similar, meaning to some degree the, you know,
the כהן has taken as it were
pre-possession of the, of the what do you call it, of the
תרומה, but he has not... but the בעל הבית baal habayis in
a way... yeah... but somehow the בעל הבית baal habayis has not
yet taken it back yet.
So it's... I don't know, I'm a little bit... I'm a little
bit... what? Meaning somehow it's because since... let me just read רש"י
one more time. It made... it made some sense last night. Hold
on.
Right, exactly.
Basically the way רש"י says it is like this: From the בעל
הבית'ס baal habayis's perspective, I did... there's nothing left for me to
do. Um, you know, I gave the money to the כהן and
therefore and... so my side of any transactional act is done and
therefore I can't say I haven't completed my act and I want
to and I want to reverse myself. But from the כהן'ס kohen's
perspective, he, he in a way didn't finish his thing, the way
רש"י says it is because he hasn't yet taken possession and given
back the תרומות, so in a way his act is not yet
complete and therefore it allows him to somehow to, you know, to
reverse himself. I don't really fully get it but that's the idea.
Yes.
Right, like the בעל הבית baal habayis action is to give the
כהן money.
And that's done.
Right. And you've done that. You can't take that back and then
it's the כהן needs to repay and until the, the
separation happens, the repayment occurs.
Right. So the power of the, of the terms of the repayment
are in the hands of the כהן, because it's the כהן'ס kohen's
side of the transaction, right? I mean, that's helpful. So it's the
כהן'ס kohen's side of the transaction that hasn't been yet fulfilled. You
lent me the money, you made certain conditions about how I can
repay, so those conditions are binding, but somehow I who am not
yet paid haven't haven't paid back yet, I you know I somehow
I get to re... you know.
An option, like I've loaned you this money and there's an option
if you want you can pay it back by I'll take this
from this place but if you want to come in tomorrow and
say actually I have this money I want to repay you with
and keep your תרומה.
Right. But by saying it's an option a little begs the question
because why don't we just say that there's, you know, that either
side has that option? Anyway, yeah.
Somebody pays you something, they don't yet take possession... yeah, they take
their money back. Does the person who paid have any like damages?
Yeah, the גמרא said it has a מי שפרע, mi she-para, he
gets to give a curse to the other guy of the type
of a censure. But... but... yeah... no,
not really. Anyway, we'll worry about all that in בבא מציעא. Let's...
okay, let's move on. נתייאשו הבעלים אין מפרישין עליהן לפי שאין מפרישין
על האבוד. nisyashu ha-bealim ein mafrishin aleihen le-fi she-ein mafrishin al ha-avud.
If he's בעל המתייאש ba'al hamityaeish then they've lost it, with much
as פשיטא. pshita. I'm shocked by that פשיטא. pshita. I still don't
really, but okay, somehow because it's like a pre-purchase,
it's like and then אמתייאש amityaeish I lose my rights to that.
I don't again still fully get that. לא צריכא lo tzericha says
the גמרא דעקו de'aku that it's already the the the grain was
already in the straw like in already standing. And therefore and that's
when it got damaged. So מהו דתימא mah du teima I'm just
reading this through רש"י. אקנתא מילתא היא akanta milsa hi that because
it was already in the standing straw when it got damaged that
it was never really fully damaged and I never really was fully
מתייאש mityaeish because that type of grain often will recover. קא משמע
לן kamashma lan we don't say that and if I actually say
that I'm מתייאש mityaeish then that actually means that I now lose
rights to collecting the loan. Okay.
תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan the הברייתא habraisa רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר
המלווה מעות לכהן וללוי בבית דין ומתו מפריש עליהם בחזקת אותו השבט.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer hamalveh ma'os l'kohen u'l'Levi b'beis din u'meisu
mafrish aleihem b'chezkat oso hashevet. So even though in that case before
when they died I had to get permission from the heirs. Okay,
but here because I am doing it in a בית דין beis
din and again the בית דין beis din and in חז"ל are
interested in this institution working, so if I've actually made it a
sort of a you know sort of you know done it in
a more public way in a more official way, then they can
actually say in the benefit of you know all כהנים we are
allowing you to get your loan paid up with your תרומה. Like
the the rest of the כהנים are saying they're not asking for
their תרומה to be given to them. Right? I have תרומה. The
original guy I guess you know is dead, right? And basically what
what the בית דין beis din is implicitly saying is because you
borrowed it in בית דין beis din we will speak on behalf
of the כהנים and say that they are okay with you taking
this תרומה for yourself. Right? You're somehow it's as if they own
it and you keep it for yourself and they're okay with that.
Why? Because it's in their interest to have this institution work. Right?
It's in their interest in this particular case to let me keep
it and not give it to one particular כהן because everybody benefits
because we have this institution. The הברייתא habraisa actually there's a version
in the תוספתא Tosefta actually says not בחזקת אותו השבט b'chezkat oso
hashevet but ברשות אותו השבט. birshus oso hashevet. Okay, it was their
implicit
we are speaking on their behalf and we're saying that now you
can keep it for yourself. Okay. את עני בבית דין ומת מפריש
עליהם בחזקת עניי ישראל es ani b'beis din u'meis mafrish aleihem b'chezkat
aniyei Yisrael or if we're not dealing about a tribe but we're
speaking on behalf of all poor people and we're saying that don't
give us the the מעשר עני ani keep it for yourself to
pay it back. Okay. And that will make everybody happy and make
it a working institution. רבי עקיבא אומר בחזקת עניי עולם Rabbi Akiva
omer b'chezkat aniyei olam not עניי ישראל aniyei Yisrael but עניי עולם
aniyei olam of the world. מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What's the difference?
איכא בינייהו עניי כותי ika beinaihu aniyei Kuti if there are Samaritans
in the town. So רש"י says עניי ישראל aniyei Yisrael suggests like
the present עניים aniyim the ones that I normally would give the
ones of my town. So if you're speaking on their behalf let's
say there are so let's say there are no עניים aniyim in
your town no Jewish עניים. aniyim There are only Samaritans עניים. aniyim
Okay. So then if so if you say that you're speaking on
behalf of עניי עולם aniyei olam so you're speaking about the Jewish
עניים aniyim elsewhere. Okay, and therefore and therefore
it can work because you're speaking on their behalf I would have
given it to somebody not in my town and now I'm going
to keep it myself. But if you're only somehow empowered to speak
about the עניים aniyim in my town and there are no עניים
in the town that I would have given it to so then
it won't necessarily work. Okay. העשיר העני אין מפריש עליו. he'eshir he'ani
ein mafrish alav. Now let's say the עני ani gets rich. Okay,
you know then even if you do it in a בית דין
when the בית דין can speak on behalf of the כהנים and
the לויים and the עניים when you lend the money in a
בית דין only when they die. But if they actually the עני
ani gets rich then you're going to actually have to find another
עני ani to pay it up and you're not going to get
to pocket the money. Now why not? Like as long as בית
דין is making this stipulation to make the institution work let it
work also if the עני gets rich. Right? Either way I'm not
going to get I'm why should I be out getting my loan
paid up?
So in the other case if the עני died... yeah... and there's
עניי כותי aniyei Kuti in the in the town. Yeah. So you
have to give to those עניים
or you get to pocket the... in other words he owes...
No we're assuming you're not giving to עניי כותי. aniyei Kuti. Okay.
But the עני owed you money then he dies right? So what's
the גמרא saying that you have to...
I don't let's let's not belabor the עניי כותי. aniyei Kuti. It's
a little complicated. Let's just move on. Okay. So anyway וזו הכא
במה שבידו. v'zo hacha b'mah she'beyado. So in that case if the
עני gets rich even when I do it in a בית דין
I'm not the בית דין won't speak on behalf of the other
עניים and let me keep my money. Okay, only if the עני
dies. So רבנן מאי שנא למיתה דעבד תקנתא מאי שנא לעשירות דלא
עבד תקנתא? rabbanan mai shna l'misa d'avid takanta mai shna l'ashirus d'lo
avid takanta? Now why the גמרא says did they make a תקנתא
takanta to make this institution work if the עני dies but not
if the עני gets rich? Either way I'm out my money. So
the גמרא says מיתה שכיחא עשירות לא שכיחא. misa shchicha ashirus lo
shchicha. Because everybody dies. Not everybody gets rich. Okay, so therefore to
we will make this institution you know We'll deal with cases of
death, that's a regular thing, and therefore we're going to allow you
to get your money paid back. Cases of guy getting rich are
very unlikely and therefore, you know, we're not necessarily going to cover
all eventualities. So אמר okay, אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa היינו
דאמרי אינשי hainu d'amri inshi that's what people say: חברך מית אשאר.
chavrach mis ashar. If you hear that your friend died, you can
affirm that, that's probably a true report as opposed to the famous
Mark Twain, rumors of my demise or whatever are greatly exaggerated. But
איתעשר itashar but if you hear that your friend got rich, לא
תאשר lo ta'asher don't be so quick to affirm that, that's probably
not true. Okay? Current Powerball out of me is 1.3 billion dollars.
Okay, anyway. All right, good luck everybody. Okay, let's try to do
one more little piece. מת צריך ליטול רשות. met tzarich litol reshus.
If he dies, then you have to get the heirs to agree
to be willing to pay off the debt and to agree to
this arrangement, because otherwise if there's no lien, the heirs are not
obligated to pay off the debt.
תנו רבנן בברייתא be-braisa רבי אומר Rebbi omer יורשים שירשו. yorshim she-yarshu.
It only applies to heirs who inherit. So the גמרא says ומי
איכא יורשים דלא ירשו? u'mi ika yorshim d'lo yarshu? Are there heirs
that don't inherit?
אלא אמר רבי יוחנן ella amar Rabbi Yochanan יורשים שירשו קרקע ולא
שירשו כספים. yorshim she-yarshu karka v'lo she-yarshu kesafim. There has to be
actually property, okay, in order to there actually be a debt to
be collected, and only in that case, right, would you sort of,
you know, get it paid, get it paid off. So אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan
הניח מלא מחט גובה מלא מחט hiniah m'lo machat gove m'lo machat
מלא קרדום גובה מלא קרדום. m'lo kardom gove m'lo kardom. And if
the guy, now again, תוספות Tosafos actually says that this is not
so much the case of the heirs agreeing, because if the heirs
agree, there doesn't have to be קרקע. karka. The heirs can agree
to pay it off even without קרקע. This is actually a case
according to תוספות Tosafos the heirs don't agree, okay, and then I
can collect because there is a lien. That's the way תוספות reads
this. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you can only collect your
debt equal to the amount of land left over. If he left
over the value, you know, the value
of a, a pin's worth of land, you can only collect a
pin's worth, and if he left a hammer's worth of land, you
can collect a hammer's worth. You can only collect if there again,
תוספות says they don't agree, you can only collect based on the
amount of land that actually exists. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar
אפילו הניח מלא מחט גובה מלא קרדום. afilu hiniah m'lo machat gove
m'lo kardom. Even if they leave a pin's worth of land, you
can collect your whole debt. Okay, why? So כמעשה דקטיני דאביי kemaisa
d'katini d'Abaye like the story of the small fields of אביי. Abaye.
There's a story over in כתובות Kesuvos where he go, somebody the
heirs owe him a hundred dollars, he collects a field worth fifty
dollars, they give him fifty dollars to buy back the land, he
gives them back the land, he says great, that fifty dollars was
payment on half the loan, you still owe me another fifty dollars
and he takes the land back.
So anyway, so there's a way in which, since theoretically you could
keep on re-collecting, and again, because this is all a תקנה דרבנן
takkanah d'rabbanan and we want this institution to work, so therefore even
if there's a small amount of land, according to תוספות understands, even
if the heirs don't agree, we're going to let you pocket the
money and keep it again in order to smooth this institution. Okay,
well done.